So, now we have builtin the year one values in our income statement,
我们已经把第一年的数据嵌入到损益表中
but as we move to year two,
继续处理第二年的数据时
we quickly realize that it's not going to be so easy moving down the list.
却发现数据显示出错
AVGO and year one were the very first row in our original data.
AVGO 的第一年数据是原数据的第一行
But as we go further down,
而处理其他数据时
it becomes more challenging to hard-code in the row number.
直接输入行号来表示需要哪一行数据 就变得越来越难
Because what if it was CSRA or year three for HPE ticker symbol?
例如 想要股票代码 CSRA 的数据 或者 HPE 的第三年数据时 就不能这么做了
We want to match both of these criteria
需要同时满足股票代码和年份的条件
for the cell value to be pulled and placed into our dashboard.
才将相应的值代入到表格
This is where the match function comes in handy.
这里就要用到 Match 函数
So, let's walk through one example.
接下来 我们利用一个例子进行详细讲解
We're matching just one criteria, the ticker symbol.
我们刚刚只匹配了一个条件 — 股票代码
Again, it's the empty dashboard we're trying to fill,
这是我们想填充的表格
and this is the data we want to pull from.
而这是我们需要提取的数据
I've gone ahead and hidden the extra financial metrics that we were showing earlier.
这里原本还有几列其他财务指标 已经暂时隐藏起来
So, right now, we're trying to match just the AVGO ticker symbol, just one criteria.
刚刚 我们只匹配了股票代码 AVGO 这一种条件
So to do that,
现在
I've replicated that in this worksheet here.
我并列显示了所需的工作表
So you can see we have the ticker symbol,
第一列是股票代码
I'm going to go ahead and hide this, and the total revenue.
隐藏不需要的一列 接着一列是总收入
We're trying to, in our dashboard,
我们希望表格里
select the value that meets at least this ticker symbol.
选择至少符合这一个股票代码的值
So, we want the INDEX to,
那么 在使用 INDEX 函数时
we don't want to hard-code the number one here.
就不是在函数里直接输入行号 1
We just wanted to match it when the ticker symbol matches AVGO.
而是当股票代码匹配为 AVGO 时 能直接匹配对应的行
So, we need to plugin the position for it.
这是位置的匹配
So, MATCH can return the number representing the position in the ticker symbol array.
满足条件时 利用MATCH 函数 就可以返回股票代码范围中相对位置的编号
So this is the ticker symbol array.
这是股票代码范围
I'll go ahead and actually call it ticker_symbol.
将这个范围命名为 ticker_symbol
We'll look for a MATCH H2 here,
函数 MATCH H2
that's the ticker symbol,
也就是这个股票代码
ticker symbol_array is the one here,
Ticker_symbol 范围就是指这个区域
and we're saying if this match type value is one,
如果匹配查询方式是 1
MATCH will look for the largest value that is less than or equal to the lookup value.
MATCH 就会查找小于等于查找值的最大值
If MATCH type is zero,
如果匹配查询方式是 0
MATCH looks for the first value that is exactly equal to the lookup value.
则会查找完全等于查找值的第一个值
There is another MATCH type negative one that looks for
还有另一种匹配查询方式是 -1
the smallest value that is greater than or equal to the lookup value.
查找的是大于等于查找值的最小值
I'm providing some example for this in the text box below.
我们在下方文本框举了例子
So, we're going go ahead in zero because we want MATCH
假设 查询方式是 0
to look for the position in this array,
现在 MATCH 要查找的是
ticker_symbol array, that matches AVGO,
Ticker_symbol 范围里匹配 AVGO 的位置
which matches this condition that we're trying to meet.
这个单元格就是我们设的第一个匹配条件
So, we referred to this lookup value.
也就是 MATCH 函数里的查找值
This is the lookup value highlighted in blue,
我们用蓝色高亮显示查找值
ticker_symbol is actually referring to this ticker symbol right here,
Ticker_symbol 是指这一列股票代码
and zero is the condition we're trying to meet.
0 是我们的匹配查询方式
Then we hit Enter there,
按 Enter 键
it gives us the value one.
返回的值是 1
Place this here so you can see the formula,
我把函数公式写在这里 以便你参考
but I had to do the Ctrl + Shift + Enter again,
要返回结果则要同时按 Ctrl + Shift + Enter 键
and this is the value of return.
这是返回的值
So, we want the value one to show up here inside the INDEX function,
我们把这个值 1 嵌入 INDEX 函数的这个位置
and that's why we just plugin whatever we take as a MATCH into the INDEX function,
我们也可以把 MATCH 函数的整个公式嵌入到 INDEX 函数
because it's looking for.
因为正如提示所见
Let me show you that. So, it's looking for the row number,
INDEX 函数的这个位置 表示行号
and that row number's provided by the MATCH function.
而 MATCH 函数返回的值就是所需的行号
As you can see, the column number right here is the
这里的列号为 0
zero because we're saying stay within the total revenue array,
表示局限在总收入一列的范围内
match the very first value in terms of row number but stay within the zero column number.
匹配符合行条件的第一个值 但局限在列 0 即该列本身
When we do this, it gives us this value.
最后返回的是这个值
I've again placed it here so that you can see what
我把公式写在这里
the formula looks like and what it gives,
供你参考
and it's the same value that is given by having the MATCH function is there.
这和嵌入 MATCH 函数一样 会返回同样的值
So, we can put this MATCH function inside the INDEX function,
所以 也可以把这个 MATCH 函数嵌入到 INDEX 函数中
and it tells INDEX which cell to pull
INDEX 函数会从相应的单元格中提取
the total revenue value from and it returns the value to us.
并返回总收入的值